so hello everybody and
Good evening everyone. And brother, I have to agree
This guy likes the first class and he is
Still I refresh once.
And he is still going like
I am.
Classes are running from 11:00 am. End
He still like with the same energy. I
I did not see him taking a break, meaning salute again.
Too Hit Energy ji brother continuously
seven what is it going to be 8 hours 8 hours
There are going to be 8 hours of continuous teaching.
The longest class I've ever had is Let Me
Tell you I took it I think two or three years ago
It will be and that means I
I have taken it frequently for five to six hours.
Classes for 5-6 hours, ah, which is my favorite
The Longest Class That Was
that was
7 [nasal sound] of hours
Class, 7 hours class. And brother's
Today is the first class. [Laughter]
It's about to be 8 hours. This is
Phenomenal Phenomenal
Huge respect to him. Because
[suddenly loud breathing]
[sound of deep breathing]
I am the same, now you may feel like
that I
If you have liked it here then praise it.
I have been. And it is worth praising.
Because I brought it with this thought in mind. This is a thought
It was like he is a very hard working
Person and again kudos to him. Kudos to
Snow. [nasal sound]
Again I think someone went from there to here also
Is. But again congratulations to him.
Because the main thing is that the process
Recognizing is very important. you people
I also give life lessons to them. Correct
Is? I also say that the hard work you
You do it very well to recognize it.
It is important. appreciate him
It is important. What will the result be?
It doesn't matter. But at least we
It is important to appreciate the process. End
Congratulations to him. Congratulations to
Prashant Sir. Let us go. So
Let's start.
Today's lecture of ours ended with Sir telling me
Actually, one thing motivated me.
I would like to speak. Motivated another one
Because now SSC has to take long classes
The exams of K are going on for a long time.
Those SSCs are not even being scheduled.
K exams. It's been a long time. so me
I am not getting a chance to take it. Now these
Seeing your Prashant Bhaiya, seeing me
I am also getting motivation. And I just
You won't believe it just yet. They
Messaged the team that I want the content.
I want a class to be scheduled tomorrow.
Well, tomorrow is packed because brother
I am not going to stop. Advance completed tomorrow
Will get it done. Like you are getting your arithmetic done today
Are. I will get the full advance done tomorrow. And in the morning
Jindal Sir will conduct current affairs weekly. So
It is packed but I will still take class tomorrow.
Ok? well. Let's get started. Today
Our July current affairs are here.
I am going to pay. Ok? And I am a railwayman
Let me tell the aspirants that your
Something very important on 15th August
Announcement is coming for Railway Students
For. Ok? So let's start and
Rest of the Group D exam will be held from 3rd August.
It has begun. So let's see how it goes
exam. This is our Lamini Yamal. Ok?
From Spain who won the FIFA World Cup
Of. You see, the buses are there but the guys
Made the team win the World Cup. well then
Let's start with the current affairs of the month of July.
Affairs with the National News section
Ours is from there. So first of all
CDSO That Is Central Duck Standard
Control Organization Has Granted
Marketing Authorization for the Dengue Alt
Tetravalent vaccine Qudenga.
What is cudenga? Tetravalent of Dengue
There is a vaccine. Manufactured by Takeda
GMBA Germany. Ok? This is the first dengue
This is a vaccine that has been approved in India.
In India by CDSO. It is a developed
Using recombinant DNA technology. To you
You should know whether it is dengue or
Then what we call dengue, this is a
Is it a viral disease or a disease?
Take it or it is a disease. Ok? you are sick
Your platelet count falls
Are in the body. platelet count, that
Drastically reducing begins. And
Which family does the virus belong to? So
virus that belongs to the family that is
Flavivirus. Ok? So this is for you
It is important to be careful. And for this
Which is a vector, vector means that
Which mosquito transmits it?
To this virus. This virus moves on its own
I will not go. So you should keep this in mind that
Your mosquito that is female.
Which one? Aedes aegypti. Anopheles which occurs
That happens to you in malaria. Joe Ades
aegypti is what causes dengue and chikungunya
It happens in. Will keep this in mind. Next is
Ancient Buddhist Site of Very Very
The varied ancient Buddhist site of Sarnath
was inscribed on the UNESCO World
Heritage List at the 48th session of the World
Heritage Committee Held in Buenos Aires Republic
of Korea making it India's 45th World
Heritage property. India's 45th
It has become a World Heritage Property. And from this
The first one that was made was Maratha Military
Landscape which was number 44. Ok? These
The thing you have to take care of. The Inscribe
Serializable Property Compares to Component
Parts of Chaukhandi Stupa. Ok? which is
Archaeological Remains of Sarnath Dham
Stupa, Dharmarajika Stupa and Mulang
Mulang post cut. It's a very strange name. Correct
Is? Mulagand Gakuti Viharaya which is an Ashokan Pillar
Apart from its archaeological remains
You can see it here. Location
You should know. It is Varanasi. and you
Should also know that Sarnath is right here
One is the Deer Park built by Gautam Buddha.
He gave his first sermon. Is
No? By what name do we know it?
which we know as the Dhamma Chakra
Enforcement. That is turning the wheel of law.
Dhamma
cycle
Enforcement. Ok? Turning the Wheel of Law.
This was the first sermon given by Gautam Buddha.
The one denoted by the wheel
He gave it here. So Sarnath
Keep in mind that this is the 45th World Heritage Site.
UNESCO as a property
Has been recognized. Republic of Busan
This committee was formed in Korea.
It has got recognition there.
Meaning the announcement has been made. which Ministry of
Environment Forest and Climate Change Haze
designated the Natural History Museum
that Mizoram University is in Aizawl which
That this is the capital. As a Designated
Repository of the Biological Diversity
NHM Act of 2002 that is natural
History Museum Becomes India's 21
Designated Repository. Ok? The
Biological Diversity Act of 2002
Works through three-tier system National
Biodiversity Authority State
Biodiversity Boards and
Biodiversity Management Committees. So
We have to take care of the natural resources of Mizoram.
NHM is a history museum. This
Notified 21 designated
Repository. You have to keep this in mind where
Our ancient repositories
It will be kept here. Ok? So you see this
Can. India's Updated National
Biodiversity Strategy and Action Plan
204 to 30 Is the Country's Road Map for
Implementing Cunning Montreal Global
Biodiversity Framework and Halting
Biodiversity Loss by 2030. Hulting's
This means stopping biodiversity which is harmful to the environment.
Diversity is being eroded. Losing
Is. When do we celebrate Biodiversity Day?
With a long term vision of living
In Harmony with Nature by 2050. From 2024
This National Biodiversity up to 30
This is a strategy and action plan. Ok?
It was related by the sorry released by the
Union Minister of State for Environment
Forest and Climate Change at Coop No. 16
at the Convention on Biological
Diversity in Black Colombia. Ok? The
Plan Sets 23 National Biodiversity
Targets. Kamaraj Port Becomes India
Second major port with the 18 meter draft
Capability Boosting India's Maritime
Competitiveness. So you should keep this thing in mind
It has to be kept in mind that the Kamaraj Port
Where is the location? and you should also know
We know it as Enor Port.
Are. And this is India's first major
It is a corporatized port. That is, the one who
In a way, what do private players do?
Are? Let's run it. 13 Major Ports in India
Are. This is the only one among the 13. out of 13
Three are in Tamil Nadu itself. Enori Joe Kamaraj
Which is what we are discussing right now. Chennai and
What you don't see down here is
This is your Token port that we remember so much.
Let's say it broke and fell down. Balance
You can see it all here. Kandla which
There is a title port. Deendayal Upadhyay
Known as port. And whatever your
This is your port in That Is Kolkata.
Which we call Shyama Prasad Mukherjee Port
Know by name. So India's second
Major port has been built with a with a what with
A meter draft capability boosting
India's Maritime Competitiveness. So this
The thing you have to keep in mind is its location
That also becomes important.
Because Tamil Nadu is the state with the most
Number of Major Ports in India. Ok?
So you have to keep this thing in mind. Ok? Correct
Is? Let's come to the next one. And that is the
Seventh Meeting of the Governing Body of National
Campa was held in Coimbatore under the
Chairmanship of Union Minister for
Environment Forest and Climate Change.
Now what is Campa? Campa Stands For
Compensatory Afforestation Fund Fund Management
and Planning Authority. So this is campa a
Has a stuttery body. any constitutional body
Not there. Ok? And its service
The governing meeting was held in Coimbatore.
And which is good for our environment and forests.
Bhupendra Yadav is the Climate Change Minister
He has hosted it. Ok?
In which there is Misty Scheme which will be implemented in 2023
Mangroves in 2023
Initiative for Shoreline Habitats and Tazable
Income is simple. Just remember that you
Is. MC Mangrove Mangrove Conservation
Had taken it. Was launched in 2023. 3 year
For 26 to 2026. But later 3 years
It was further extended to 2029
For till. With an additional Rs 500 crore taking
The outlay to 600 crores. That means the first 100
It was crores. Just got an additional 500. So
This means a total outlay of ₹600 crore here.
Went. A New Astha Forest Conservation Scheme Was
Approved with an initial corpus of ₹000
Crore for 2026 to 27 to 2030 to 31 to conserve
Nearly 15,000 sacred groups
15,000 Sacred Groups to Conserves
To do. What are sacred groups?
Are? Like if you ever go to North East etc.
If you ever go on a trip, to Meghalaya etc.
There you will get to see many forests.
Will meet. Ok? And there in the forest
This means that you cannot take even a single leaf from there.
Can go. Many Rudrakshas to you
Will be visible. a lot of things to carry
You will see the stuff. But you are a leaf
Can't take it. It is considered because
A bad omen to him. Because if you take
Because it is believed that it is a sacred grove
It is where the gods reside. Joe Deetz
they reside there and if
If you steal from there, they will see you.
been through the DTs and you get it
If there is punishment, it is not allowed.
take away from. Ok? So they are
Our secret groups. So to them
Faith to Conserve Forest Conservation
The scheme has been approved involving ₹3000 crore
Will be inserted.
There is a scheme from 2026, 27 to 30, 31
And 15,000 secret groups are included in this
Will be conserved. So, this is something you should keep in mind
Have to keep it. Some major decisions that were taken further
If there were, then there is no truth, any data or fact in it.
Not there. So, you can skip. One
You can read the bar. But something like this from here
Chances of being asked are low. Ok? Four.
Now this is a fact. Four Four Major Wild
Life Projects over Dick Declared River
Dolphin Project Snow Leopard Fuzz Two
Indian Rhinoceros Conservation and a Pan
India Plan for Wild Water Buffalo. Now
You should know that Joe Snow Leopard is Mainly Joe
Yours
Hemis National Park is very famous in Ladakh.
for Snow Leopard and whatever our
Khelo India Winter Games are held in it
Our Sheene Shee mascot is who is
Nothing but a snow leopard, isn't it?
Should Know and Continued Support Was
Approved for the conservation of Shanghai in the
Manipur. What is Shanghai? Brow Antler Deer.
If you remember, in Manipur we have a
Let's read about floating lakes and a
Also read about National Park. So
Which floating lake is yours? whom we
It is called Loktak Lake. Ok? This we
Known as Loktak Lake and this is it
You will see your cable here.
Lamjau National Park: Things You Should Know
We need Ramsar sites in our
Two of our Rams in Montreux record
There are wetlands. Ek to keb ye cable lamjo
National Park and the second one is of your Rajasthan
Keoladeo National Park. So right here
You get to see the Shanghai deer and it
It is also the state animal of Manipur. Union
Environment Minister Bhupendra Yadav address
No, I remember Bhupendra Jogi.
Frequently. Inaugurated the Centre of Excellence
on human wildlife conflict at
WIS SECON Coimbatore and launched
Gave. Ok? and launched the National Human
Wildlife Conflict Portal. So this
Keep in mind that what we are discussing now
Were. Ok? what we were just discussing
So under that, this is WII SECOND
What has been done to this in Coimbatore now?
This thing has been innovated, please keep it in mind
Will keep it ok by Bhupendra Yadav ji
It is clear and this was the seventh meeting we just had.
Have seen the Seventh Meeting of the National Board
For Wildlife and Wildlife Day we
Sorry, when do we celebrate Biodiversity Day?
We do? So on Biodiversity Day we
Let's celebrate on 22nd of May. And
When do we celebrate Wildlife Day?
Are? Why? When do we celebrate the
Wildlife Day?
Its call is coming. It's okay. So Wild
When do you celebrate Life Day? third of
Celebrate March. On March 3rd.
Ok? Let's come to the next one. Prahlad
Joshi Innovated the White Rabbit Technology
Based Indian Standard Time Dissemination
Demonstration Network at the Regional
Reference Standards Laboratory in Bor. Now
This is the news Prahlad Joshi, now you know
You must have found out. I don't know yet
that we have a new Education Minister.
after the resignation of Dharmendra Pradhan
Yes. Earlier he was the Minister of Consumer Affairs.
There used to be affairs. So being in that
Department in that Ministry being the
Minister of that ministry who
Department of Consumer Affairs is in Leeds
The One Nation One Time in collaboration with
CSIR National Physical Laboratory and
ISRO. which is white rapid technology u u
What does she use? Precision Time
Protocol for Highly Accurate Time
Synchronization of the Legal Meteology Rules
2025 Establish Indian Standard Time as
India's Sole Mandatory Legal Time Reference
To Bolster National Time Severity Governance
and Cyber ​​Security. So a little bit of information
Should be that Rabbit Technology White
What is Rabbit Technology and its benefits
Where is it being used? Indian
Standard Time Dissemination Demonstration
To develop the network
It has been used in. Ok? PM
Modi flagged off India's first hydrogen
Powered passenger train which operates on the
Jind Sonipat route in the Haryana. So Haryana
I operate this Jind Sonipat route here.
India's first hydrogen powered passenger train
The train has been run. We give you everything
Every month we see something or the other from hydrogen.
Let's take it. Green hydrogen from all of this. Is
No? So the first hydrogen powered train
Haryana has been run on the Sonipat route
In. Ministry of Civil Aviation
[deep breathing sound] [sudden sharp intake of breath]
Approved India's First Private Point
In Space Instrument Approach Procedure
For helicopter operations at the Undavalli
Airports that you should see where
will get? In Andhra. Point in Space
Procedures Utilize Advanced Satellite
based navigation to enable helicopters to
Perform Precise Instrument Approaches
Eight helicopters making conventional landings
Infrastructures. Ok?
So you have to keep in mind where to launch it.
Where is Undanvali Heliport located?
in Andhra Pradesh there okay so this is a little
I have to keep this in mind, okay, okay, let's go and
Who is the Minister of Civil Aviation now?
Ram Mohan Naidu is the Minister of Civil
A team of researchers has unveiled
Five new species of lichen forming
Fungi Belonging to the Genus Allographa n
Important Indicator of Forest Health and
environmental quality because of their
Sensitivity to pollution and habitat
Changes from the Western Ghats of India.
Five new species of lichen forming
Fungi. what are lichen forming fungi
Are? What are lichens? So lichen
Actually there is a symbiotic relationship.
Fungus means fungus which is called in Hindi
And algae which is called Shail in Hindi
Are. The symbiotic relationship between these two
There is a relationship. with all the fungus algae
Do not build relationships. make something
So they are called like forming algae.
Fungi speak. Ok? So these are allographs
that belong to phylum that belong to genus
I belong. Ok? So these now
identified as a
Forest health is an important indicator
Of. I have also taught you that lichen
These are your natural indicators.
They act as such. How? Natural
They act as indicators that tell us
Tell us about climate change and so on.
Are. Why? because they are responsive to
The changes in the pH level. which is our litmus test
Paper is made from lichen only.
Ok? That purple dye is dye
And it belongs to Thallophytaphylum.
So you should know a little about this thing.
Ok? Done. Now the five new species here
You don't need to know their names.
Is. Allographa karke allographa nayake hai.
Ok? Named after Sanjeev Nayak
It was named after a Kerala state.
Allographa is Keralaness, right? So different names
Is. Everything is in the name of allographa. They
You don't need to remember the name. Bus
There are five new species. Allographa is the genus.
You should know this. Just India is
Nearing completion of the Mumbai Ahmedabad High
Speed ​​Rail Masher. Its First Bullet Train
Corridor Which Will Set a New Standard
for high-speed rail with a speed up to
350 km per hour are significantly faster than
180 kmph design speed of Vande Bharat
Trance
Okay, so we're going to complete this.
Marshall is okay that is Mumbai Ahmedabad
High Speed ​​Rail First Bullet Train Corridor
Hoga ok with a design up to 350 km
But it is significantly faster than 180 kmph
R Design Speed ​​of Vande Bharat. So Vande
India has 180. You can see from it
Approx. two times. Isn't it? It
Belongs and it is being developed using
The Japanese Shinkansen technology
It is being developed using it. First
The section which will connect Surat
From Bilmora which is in Gujarat itself. Correct
Is? Which will open on 15th August 2027 next
The year end will be completely complete
It will become operational by 2029. Ok?
Ok? You can see this is about 508
Km There will be a corridor which is written here
Not there. Ok? This entire corridor will be
Its approximate length will be 508 km. of
Will happen. Ok? Well, you can see
Seven high-speed rail corridors are also being developed.
Will be done. Covering nearly 4000 km.
Have been identified for future
Development. So for future development
Developed seven high-speed rail corridors
Will go. Delhi to Varanasi, Varanasi,
Patna, Siliguri. Chennai, Bengaluru,
Bengaluru, Hyderabad, Chennai, Hyderabad,
Mumbai, Pune and Pune, Hyderabad. Ok?
What has India hosted? Now
You should know what BRICS is, BRICS Summit
India is going to host it this year.
Ok? So the different summits that take place
You will have all those in India. BRICS
Women Working Group meeting in Kochi
happened in. Third BRICS Transport
The ministerial meeting took place in Nagpur. Now remember
Put it like this that the Ministry of our road
Transport and Highways. Who is it? Who
Is? Where is ethanol uncle Gadkari from?
From Nashik in Maharashtra. Ok? So Nashik
Nagpur is nearby. Ok? so that's why
Remember to do this. Ok? Due 2026
BRICS Labour and Employment Ministry
The meeting took place in Hyderabad. 16th BRICS
Health Ministry meeting was held in Chandigarh.
This is how you remember Chandigarh. Environment
It is very good. Ok? People of Chandigarh
They are healthy. Like your Buddha.
I am from Chandigarh. So like Kamal Sir, right? So
Since you are from Chandigarh, you are quite healthy. This
Remember it this way. BRICS heads off
Where did the anti-drug agencies meeting take place?
In Guwahati. BRICS meeting on
Traditional Complimentary End
Integrative Medicine. this in Chandigarh
It has happened to you too. Ok? People who are healthy
Yes, those who are healthy, why are they healthy?
Are? Because the medicine is taking time
That's why he is healthy on time. remember like this
Please Keep. IIT Tirupati Hosted 2026 BRICS
Working Group Meeting on Jio Special
In technology. Who hosted? IIT
Tirupati. Many ITs have opened.
No, and you should know that
It's BRICS, right? So in BRICS right now
It is not just five countries. Firstly
Brazil, Russia, India and China used to be
Were. When South Africa 2010 was formed in 2009
I had joined. But now you know
That apart from these, other countries have also joined
Are. As Egypt joins,
Ethiopia is added. Ok?
Indonesia has joined, Iran has joined
Is. Ok? And your ah UAE is added.
So how many countries do you have now?
It is in it. Ok? So you know this thing
Should be. Ok? Ok? and Indonesia
He is the latest one to join it.
Union Minister for Labour and Employment
Inaugurated the 15th BRICS Trade Union
Forum Summit in Hyderabad. So we just saw
Where did the labour incident take place? Labor and
Your Employment Meet in Hyderabad
Hui. So you can relate it to that.
India hosted the Third BRICS Ministerial
Meeting on Disaster Risk Reduction.
BRICS Joint Statement Adopted to
Advance Global Disaster Resilience.
Ok? Third BRICS Ministerial Meeting
on Disaster Risk Reduction. India has
Host Curry. Obviously all the BRICS
The meeting is being hosted by India itself. India
Host BRICS Network University
Conference and the International Governing
Board Meeting Strengthening the Bricks Higher
Education Corporation. Is there anything to remember
Going to do? Not going to remember anything at all
No, because we already know that.
BRICS is being held in India. The
Ministry of Cooperation You know that the new
A ministry was created. Ok? So he
Celebrated its Fifth Foundation Day
Ministry of Cooperation and its
Who is the minister? You know who
Ministry of Home Affairs is your fat
Brother. Ok? Mota Bhai is leading Moha
To the Ministry of Home Affairs. India
taxi you know ministry of
This is an initiative of the corporation which is a recent
It has been run as a pilot project in
Generally in Delhi NCR and Gujarat
Two come with in Maharashtra and Rajasthan
Compete with Ola, Uber and Rapido
This will happen, this is the government's taxi.
Ok? This Cooperate The Cooperative Ride
Healing platform ah follows a faced national.
Roll out plan to reach out to 500 cities. About
It will reach out to 500 cities. The
Ministry of Steel Granted Mini Ratna
Category One status to MECON Limited to which
Ministry of Steel has Mini Ratna
MECON has been given Category One status
Limited, you have to keep this thing in mind now
This which
[deep breathing sound] [sudden sharp intake of breath]
It is Mecon Limited, that is not important to him.
It is important for us that
I asked who gets so much Category One
Who gets category two, I am not
I am saying that it is too much to ask.
There are more chances but still I will tell you
I'll give you this, you just have to take care of us.
Who Ltd. Who gave who? Ministry
Of steel. Ok? And whom else? Macon
To Ltd. So the central public sector
Enterprise must have made profits
Continuously for the last three years.
It has made profits continuously for the last three years.
Booked must have a positive net worth
and should have earned a pre-tax profit of
At least 30 crores in one of the three years.
And for category two, that enterprise must
Have made profits continuously for the
Last Three Years and Have a Positive
Net worth. The Ministry of Tribal Affairs
That is thick launch tribex a first of
Its Kind Digital Learning Platform
Dedicated to the tribal ah to tribal
Arts Culture Traditional Knowledge and Skills
Development
So this has been launched by Tribex.
Obviously Ministry of Tribal Affairs
He will do it. Who else is the Union Minister now?
For Tribal Affairs? He is Mr. Joyal
Oram Jul Oram Hai Tribal in Current
Minister. Ok? So you should pay attention to this thing
Have to keep it. The Union Cabinet
Approved by an Additional Government of India
Investment commitment of ₹30,000 crore in
The National Investment and
Infrastructure Fund NIF to Accelerate
Infrastructure Investment. So that's it
It is to be noted that the Union Cabinet
₹30,000 crore commitment in NIF
Investment commitment has just been made. So this
You have to remember a little bit well. Ok?
Ok. Let us move forward. Researchers from
India and Sri Lanka have discovered three
New Rare Species of Jumping Spiders.
So what are the three new species that are here right now?
Have they been done? Jumping has been discovered
Of spiders. Brahmagiri has got two
From the Hills and Silent Valley. Brahmagiri
Hills you can see in Wayanad, Kerala
Will meet. And you know about Silent Valley too?
Silent Valley National Park if you remember
Where it is? Palakkad. You will also find this in Kerala
Will be seen. Ok? So, with the third
Found in the mountain forests of Sri Lanka.
You will see the third one in Sri Lanka.
Sri Lanka reminded me that Sri Lanka has
Won the first gold medal. in javelin throw
If we talk about the Commonwealth, which is going to be held in 2026,
Neeraj Chopra won silver and
What is that name? Yashveer Singh won the Bronze Medal
He won in that, right? So Ramesh from Sri Lanka
His name is Ramesh. So he
Won the gold medal. Ok? Arshad Nadeem who
They were from Pakistan but they got nothing. India
got two medals each and just a while ago
This is the news. Today's news is that
India won two gold medals each in boxing.
Have gone. Do you know India in boxing?
Has received double gold medals. two gold
Medals have been received. One is Preeti Pawar and
Second by Jasmine Lamboria. as if yesterday
Us
This is Judo. So in Judo you know
Back to back, give us one identity
gota and the second I think Harsh Singh Gujral
The name is complete. So he took up judo
Both the people got the medal and even today
Our two females gave us two I think
Females gave us more gold medals
This time as compared to males. and that
Is Again a Very Good Thing. Yes Yes in Judo
We also won two gold medals yesterday. and the first
Till date we have not used common gold but gold.
Did not win a medal. and simultaneously the same
Two gold medals won within minutes of each other's debut
For that, in judo. New Delhi Hosted
And Asmita De's story is also quite
It is inspiring. New Delhi hosted the
Fifth Beamstock National Security Advisors
Meeting. Beamstuck You Should Know That Established
It happened in 1997. Head Quarters R
Located in Dhaka, Bangladesh. Beamstock Key
if we talk and you should also know that
There is SAARC, SAARC was formed in Dhaka.
In Bangladesh. But its headquarters
In Kathmandu Nepal. So the national
There are security advisors, they all came.
of Beamstock Countries. And we know you
Who is it? Ok? are the shortest in height
But the work is the toughest. Isn't it? of India
What do you keep saying to them? Why? What
Is it called India's? So Bay of Bengal
Initiative for Multisectoral Technical and
Economic Cooperation is its full form.
Bangladesh, India, Myanmar, Sri Lanka,
Thailand and Nepal and Bhutan. Instead, we
NB let's do it. Nepal and Bhutan. These
What are they? Its member countries are: you should
No it.
And he is called the James Bond of India.
Isn't it? The government has introduced the
Index of Services Production ISP
New Economic Indicator to Capture the
Performance of the Services Sector. So
The Government of India has established a new
index lch kiya that is index of
Service production. The Base Year of ISP
Has been selected as 2425. ISP Covers
Mainly the formal sector. Ah Formal Service
Sector not the informal sector. This formal
Covers the service sector and not
Take care of the informal sector. Index
of Service Production. IIP which is
Index of Industrial Production
Its
So what is the background of New Base Year?
You are not getting any noise, right? So, new bass.
What has happened to this year, the IIP
There is GDP and your
WPI for all these has become 2023-24
Is. Ok? And what does your si ah say?
Are? CPI or Consumer Price Index
If this is your 2024 then you should know this.
You need it. Ok? N Cash Launch Indias
First UPI Integrated Meal Card for
Corporate Employees Enabling Allowance
Pending by any QR merchant. So that's it
Just keep in mind that N Cash is
India's first UPI integrated meal
The card has been made. Mile card. Ok? Ok?
So its name is N Cash. And
We
This means the same as the tax-free meal offer.
Does. That's all. Ok? Up to ₹200
If you take a meal, there is no tax.
It will take place in that. Tax means GST etc.
It won't work. Isn't it? The Second Bharat Green
Hydrogen Summit Took Place at the Fikki
Federation House in New Delhi. So seconds
India Green Hydrogen Summit is held here
Pay. And
What was the theme? The theme was positioning India as
A Global Hydrogen Hub. Ok. Ok. National
Payments Corporation of India that is
NPCI partnered with the HSBC India
and JPMorgan Payments to enable real
Time Foreign Exchange Conversion and Settlement
Not that merchant, just be careful and watch
Take NPCI and HSBC in Hong Kong.
Your Shanghai bank is fine, isn't it?
HSBC has done this simply by collaborating
I have launched yours, okay, real time.
Foreign Exchange Conversion and Settlement Bus
Much of the truth is not important.
[sound of deep breathing]
Ok. The Union Minister of Health and
Family Welfare Latch The Samagra Shishu Bal
Health programs. Ok? What is this?
It is a unified national program that
Aims to provide a seamless continuum of a
Home and Community Based Care for Everyone
Child from birth to 36 months of age. Birth
From 12 to 36 months of age
seamless continuum that is of home and
Community-based care provides this. The
The ministry also has Unified Health
Interface and Interoperable Digital Network
Under the Ayushman Bharat Digital Mission as of
July 10, 2026 This mission has been created more
93.945
Ayushman Bharat Health Account Abha which we
They say that Abha ID was created by him.
Are. Ok?
Is it clear? So from birth to 3 years old
Labor for children Infant Child Health
The program has been launched. This is
Importent. Ok? Let us go.
Shake hands, friend.
India launched a weekly. The Worlds
First
The World's First Once Weekly Basel
Insulin. Ok? So Abhikali was launched.
Has gone. Right now there is the Weekly Flex Touch Pen. Correct
Is? What is this? This is a flex touch pen.
Well, this is type one and type two diabetes.
What happens to you? Why? Type One Type
What is the difference between diabetes and diabetes? Type
This one does not produce insulin at all.
Doesn't let me make it. Ok? And this in it
Insulin is produced but the body
She registers. Ok? This response
Doesn't do it. So, this is the difference between the types
In type one and type two diabetes. So, of the same
A Weekly has been launched here for this.
The World's First Weekly Insulin That
Freeze Type 2 Diabetes From Daily
Injection. You will no longer need daily injections.
Have to take it. Ok? Once Weekly Basil
You just have to take insulin. No multiple doses
You will have to take a lot. just once
Take it once a week. Ok? every day and every day
You don't have to take injections every day. Ok? Let us go
Next is The IT Kanpur Announce That It Will
Establish Centre of Excellence on Green
Hydrogen. So IT Kanpur which is green
A Centre of Excellence for Hydrogen
Will make. That's it. Ok? and its name
What will happen? Name the Centre of Excellence on
Innovative and Integrated Ecosystem for
Green Hydrogen and Ecogen. Ecogen Its
Will be the name. Take care. IIT Kanpur. And
This is your Centre of Excellence on Green
There will be hydrogen. India achieved a major
Milestone at the 49th Session of the Codex
Alimentarius Commission Cac 49 Held In
Geneva, Switzerland with the adoption of three
Global Codex Standards for Large
Cardamom Coriander and Vanilla
ok what are the codex standards
If there is a Codex Alimentarius Commission
Develops Global Food Safety and Quality
What it does is develop the standard
This cake is jointly administered by Food
This is your FAO, Food and Agriculture.
Organization and the World Health
There is an organization. Both this and this
Established jointly which food safety
What does it do to end quality standards?
Is? Monitors, regulates. So,
He is the one who gave the codex standards here.
Are. Large cardamom
Yes, coriander which is your coriander and
To vanilla. Ok? So, keep this thing in mind
Is. These three were included in the 49th Session of the Codex.
Found it. Now comes the state news.
Pay. So, are you all ready? Quick
Tell me guys. Do you know? Yes sir
Sugarcane juice big glass ₹20 petrol pump
came over
Are
Sir I want to prepare for NTPC
graduate i pass 12 this year can i buy
Your Recorded Combo Batch and Weight for
Upcoming batches ah i would advise shishupal
Yes, I just want to wait for the 15th of August because
Railway announcements on August 15th
It may be there but it is fine on our railway channel.
Just wait till 15th. ok now coming
on to this Balod District in State
News. Balod District in Chhattisgarh
has emerged as a strong community leader
Water Conservation Model Under Water Conservation Water
Bhagidari 2.0 Giving Fresh Momentum to the
Catch the Rain Movement Movement. Ok? So this
Have a Strong Country Lead Water Conservation
Under the model, this came out as water conservation water
Who is included in the partnership? Jo Balod District
He is in Chhattisgarh. Ok? of this scheme
If we talk about it or we talk about it
Water Conservation Water Partnership This will be implemented in Surat by 2024.
It was launched from. From April 1, 2024
To implement it by 31 May 2025
1.0 Surpasses Its Target of
Constructing at least 10 lakh grounds
Water Recharge Structures. That is why these
Water conservation is developed
goes. So that ground water recharge
It is possible.
Ok? Ok? Otherwise, there will be surface run-off.
Water is used and ground water is recharged
It cannot happen. To Balot District
Chhattisgarh is a strong state
As a community led water conservation model
But it is being presented.
Uttarakhand has become the sixth state. Yes
It has become the sixth state which has
Ah After Achieving the Prescribed Adult
Literacy Benchmarks under the National Education
policy which is our tertiary education policy
2020 and the Glee Which Is Understanding
of Life Long Learning for All in Society
New India Literacy Programme
Uttarakhand becomes the fully literate state
Sixth Fully Literate First Fully Literate
Tell me which one was it, the first one was your Kerala Vaz
Historically Recognized as Indias
First fully literate state in 1991.
Ok? So you should keep this thing in mind
Is. So, Uttarakhand has become your sixth.
Ok? Here the benchmark actual is 90%
I have to achieve literacy. Correct
Is? Maharashtra has become the first state
In India to Net the Maharashtra Women
Farmers Empowerment Act 2026 which
officially recognizes women as
Independent Farmers. Ok? So
Maharashtra has become the first state to
Who has activated Maharashtra Women
Farmers Empowerment Act which officially
Recognizes women as independent farmers
Recognizes them as. Correct
Is? You have to keep this thing in mind.
Maharashtra announces India's First
Proposed AI Enabled Bird Conservation
Project at Thane Greek Filming
Century. Flamingos look very beautiful
Are. Ok? I mean, this is for you to see
See you mainly in Maharashtra. So
Which in Maharashtra
Thane Creek Flamingo Sanctuary is there.
Ok? India has proposed AI
Enabled Bird Conservation Project. Ok?
Let's move on. India Commission its
First Ever Geothermal Wells in Puga Valley
Ladakh. First Geothermal Wells. you know
Geothermal means from the interior of the Earth
Heat is released. Do you know this thing? Meaning
Heat escapes from the interior. Why
Does it come out? Because what we mean
has layers such as crust, mantle
End Cor. So whatever you have here
This means that there is asthenosphere in the mantle.
The mantle has an upper solid part.
to see the asthenosphere just below it
It is available. from where magma or lava comes out
Comes. So wherever it comes from,
If there is water somewhere near it, then there is a lot of it.
It will get hot. It will get very hot. So that
As a form of energy is used.
So like there is Puga Valley in Ladakh. As
You will get to see Manikaran. have you ever
Have you heard about Manikaran? So Manikaran
Where are you at? In Himachal Pradesh. So
All these are huge sources of geothermal energy.
There are sources in India. So right here
What happened to your geothermal bill?
Commissioned. Marking a Critical
Step Toward Establishing the Nations
First One Megawatt Geothermal Power
project. Union Culture and Tourism
Minister Gajendra Singh Shekhawat inaugurated
India's First of Its Kind Space
Exploration Gallery. Where? Bhopal MP
In. This is your first space.
Inaugurated the Exploration Gallery
Gajendra Singh Shekhawat, Cultural Tourism
He is a minister. Innogate your fat brother
Kia first fuzz of museum of world in
Kolkata, West Bengal. Delhi Government
Loch to New to New Heritage Conservation
Schemes are monuments are pride
Initiative. Ok? The Delhi Government
Launched under Monument R
Pride Initiative. What kind of schemes are these?
So there's the Monument Friends program and
There is a financial assistance grant. According to this
What is it that whatever your
Whatever these private companies are, these
She is working there, what should she do?
Is? One way to adopt them is
For the preservation of monuments and their
Have to work. Do you understand? The government also
Work is also being outsourced using free funds.
Isn't it? [nasal sound] Son
If you want to live here, you will have to do it. Ok?
So you should know that whoever is ASI
Monuments that come under rejection
Launched under Friends Programs
Is. Can be any NGO, PSU
It can also be a private company.
Is. So they will be given 5 years or 5 years
So you adopt him. Ok? any
Further financial assistance to the monument
Will be given. Institutions that will be eligible
Up to ₹2 crore Up to ₹ crore
Financial grant will be given. Meaning
Borjuli Wetland in Assam has been notified
As a Biodiversity Heritage Site for the
Conservation of wild rice Oryza ruf Pagon
whose name is. So there is Borjaili Wetland which
In Assam it has been notified as a
Biodiversity Heritage Site. Ok?
Sirsa Kinnow Have you eaten Kinnow? oranges
Looks like a but plays big tittily
Is. It received a GI tag becoming
Haryana has become the first fruit to be given the GI tag.
found. This is from Sirsa. Sirsa which is in Haryana
I buy Kinnow from 200 years old Jodhpur
It's clogs, right? Has earned GI tag
Boosting the Identity of Rajasthan Rinode
Leather Craft. Ok? Take care of your socks.
Slippers. Ok? Uttarakhand Government has
Inaugurated the State's first dedicated
Geographical Indication Product. GI
Products Gallery at the Forest Training
Academy, which is where you can see it.
Will I get it? In Haridwar. Ok? of the state
First dedicated GI product gallery
In Uttarakhand. We have related to Uttarakhand
And what news did you read just now about Uttarakhand
Sixth state becomes 100% fully literate
State under the glee. Ok? UP LUCKNOW
Chief Minister's Teachers Cashless Medical
Scheme Chief Minister Education Teacher Teacher
Those who are teachers, they will get up to Rs 5 lakh.
Coverage will be available here. Ok? annually
Family. Ok?
To provide free health coverage.
Ok? Let us go.
I don't know why I feel like drinking Fanta.
It has been happening all along. Chhattisgarh becomes the first
State in India to adopt a risk based
Regulatory Framework for Businesses to Buy
Passing the Chhattisgarh ease of doing sorry by
Passing the Chhattisgarh Ease of Doing Business
Act of 2026. The first state of India to become
Is. Ok? who adopted the risk
Based Regulatory Framework for Businesses
Which has enacted the Chhattisgarh Ease of Doing Business Act
passed to. So the first state of India has been formed
Chhattisgarh. Risk Based Regulatory
Framework adopter. The JNK
Government declared leprosy an
Notifiable disease with immediate effect. Correct
Is? Ok? We are laughing at leprosy
Also known as disease. you know
Is
What do we paint?
Sir ji Jindal sir's marathon pdf.
Good
A, I will talk to Jindal sir. Ok. I
I think there was some error in the first one.
Just look at it once. still engaged
What sir?
We are still engaged, you have to admit.
[nasal sound]
I think it will cross 9-10 hours today.
said the Jammu and Kashmir Government
Declared leprosy or notifiable disease
We have seen this. Ok? access to this
Also known as disease. And
Leprosy you should know that Mycobacterium
The bacteria caused by leprae
It happens because of. Union Minister
Jyotiraditya Scindia left a five year old
Road Map 2025 to 30 Title Mission
Golden Spice to Boost Production. Correct
Is? Processing and Global Branding of
Meghalaya's GI tagged Lakadong turmeric
Where is Lakadong Turmeric from? Of Meghalaya.
Ok? Ok? So keep this mission in mind.
5 Years Complete Road Under Golden Spice
This is the map made by Jyotiraditya Scindia.
It is launched here. ₹175 crore mission
Golden Spice Lunch to Boost Meghalaya's Legumino
Turmeric. Punjab has been connected with 27
Global Destinations Across North America,
UK, Europe, Australia with the launch of
Air India's Easy Connect. Air India's
Easy Connect is launched in hub and spoke model.
Ok? Ok? Hub and spoke something like this
Operates in the manner at Shri Guru
Ramdas Ji International Airport. Ok? 27
Connected to a global destination
Punjab has it now. Ok? Punjab people are
Even far away - Canada, US, Australia
A lot of people are going there these days. The MP
Legislative Assembly passes the Uniform Civil
Code UCC Making It The Fourth State In
India to adopt a common legal framework
For personal laws. Fourth state to become UCC
The one who adopts. Which was the first? just
Tell me. Which was the second one? Which was the third one?
And which was the fourth one? tell me fast. No
So whatever happened, you got beaten. Uttarakhand,
Gujarat, Assam and now the fourth one has become ours
MP. Ok? MP Declares 2027 as the
Year of youth. Wow Mohan Yadav ji.
Ok.
Property Property Thief. Why? My Youth
My pride. Conclave
2027 has been declared the Year of Youth.
Has gone. From The Tripura Government Tripura
It is he who gave you your identity and your tomorrow.
Won gold medal for India. So the
Tripura Government has made the singing of
The full version of the national song Vande Mataram
Followed by the National Anthem Jana Gana Mana compulsory
in all schools across the state during
Daily morning assemblies. So Daily Morning
It was made compulsory in assemblies.
that Vande Mataram will be sung first and then
Later Jana Gana Mana will be sung. Ok?
Rajasthan becomes the first Indian state to
Sign the Framework for Action Advance Clean
Energy Driven Sustainable Development with the
International Solar Alliance. So become the first state
Gaya Rajasthan who signed
Framework for Action on Advanced Clean
Energy with regard to the International Solar
Alliance.
Oho Supreme Court has given Rs 1500 crore to Kukrel
Night Safari Project approved
Which will be built in Lucknow. Ok? and to do so
This is India's first urban night safari.
It will become the world's fifth after Singapore,
Thailand, China, Indonesia. Accept
I will have to, I will have to accept it. Ok? UP also
I am moving ahead now. Ok? one time
That was when both UP and Bihar were backward. Bihar
So it remained the same but UP is a little ahead
It has increased. Ok? That is a very good
Thing. The Supreme Court has declared almost
₹1,500 crore Kukrail is being developed in
will be? In Lucknow. You will enjoy it. Now let's see
By when will it be developed and ready? but fun
Will come.
India has approved it's fun friend.
I am telling the truth. I mean when I mean a
I have been there only once. Last year in 2025
Rajaji National Park in December.
I had fun brother. December means in December
Had gone. It was very cold. perfect morning time
Was. There wasn't much of anyone. Someone showed up
Was not there. Meaning such a tiger had never been seen before.
The leopard was not seen. If you look like this, it looks normal
There were dears etc. But there is a suspense, isn't it?
I had so much fun as if it wasn't there. I mean [laughs]
I was feeling like a king. tell me the truth
Have been. I had a lot of fun. Absolutely and this
I want to enjoy it again and again. India
Has approved.
But money is a burden, friend. India has
Approved Its First Utility Scale. 100
Mega Ah that's your 100 megawatt or so
Vanadium Red Redox Flow Battery Energy
Storage system is for deployment at
Khavda Solar Park in the Gujarat OK Gujarat
Latch The Cyber ​​Financial Fraud E0 FIR
Service is good for financial fraud
Where is the EZero FIR service in Gandhinagar?
E0 means where there is no such
Not the specific police station from where
Yes, the police station is there, anywhere is fine.
and we say zero FIR, E means ho
You are watching this electronically digitally.
Brother, you are not looking at a banyan tree.
This is in Munger, Bihar.
You can see its roots which are 700 years old.
The roots penetrated the ground completely
Munger is 700 years old, is this right?
Age is the oldest accurately dated place in Bihar
Specimen using scientific radiocarbon
Radiocarbon dating was used to
Rather than traditional or historical
Brother of records, this Chunnu is here
Come on, how many years do you want to make this, brother?
I know this is a thousand years old. yes here
But this witch comes dancing in the night
It has happened. So if anyone goes by it
Not there. Are you watching, son? so something like this
Not there. Chunnu Munnu was not asked.
Here in Pe Actual asked from C1-14
Is. Carbon 14 is what we use.
For radio dating. and found out from him
Has gone. Can't you see, I'm not that type
It looks like a tree. You like this type
The tree does not look like a banyan tree in which
That she does the ghost dance. enter here
She dances at night, just like I am telling you
We. Ok? At night we
The Ahmedabad AH Municipal Corporation AMC
Set a new Guinness World Record by
Planting over 3.61 lakh saplings in
Just one hour. Ahmedabad in 1 hour
The Municipal Corporation planted 3.6 lakh trees.
are utilizing the Miyakawi Afforestation
Method. [nasal sound]
[sound of deep breathing] Okay?
There is the Miankawi method, there is the Japanese method.
under which fermentation is done
In urban areas. And that is a very
Also a good thing. Ok? Hum Woh Diyaan Mein
to become. So why are witches always white?
Does she wear it? I'll have to ask the witch now.
Why do you wear white? Ok. So Kerala
Latch The Digital Square Education Initiative
As part of its 100 Day Action Plan for
The Education Sector. So Kerala launched
Digital Square Education Initiative. Ok?
The film has become Tamil Nadu's first fully
Operational Climate Resilient Village. Ok?
Tamil Nadu's first fully operational
Climate Resilient Village is built under the
Tamil Nadu Climate Change Mission.
Jharkhand Film Development Corporation Limited
Sign an MoU that is Memorandum of
Understanding with the Satyajit Rail film
and Television Institute to establish the
Jharkhand Film and Television Institute in
Ranchi. So you have to keep in mind that the
Jharkhand's Film Development Corporation is
He has signed a Memorandum of
Understanding with Satyajit Ray Lifetime
Televis Institute. Ok? So under this
Jharkhand Film and Television
The institute will be built in Ranchi. Mister
Kakulam district in Andhra Pradesh
Will get a full-fledged airport
The common citizen of the country flies under the flight
If there is a scheme, then under that Sri Kakulam
The district which is in Andhra Pradesh
A full-fledged airport is also available.
Is.
Ok. Come on and tell me the rest of the good
The Udan scheme is when it was launched and
How many outlets are there in it?
If you went then keep in mind that the flight
The common citizen of the country should fly so that he can
We can blow up civilians, it's okay on the road.
It was launched in 2016 and launched
Meaning, for how long was it done and why?
The first flight under this was Na Udan
Under this she went from Shimla to Delhi. To you
Should know. OK and
It was launched in 2016 and is fine.
And what do you say right now, 2000 March?
The news is from 2026 where the modified
The flight was approved. come now
They go for international news.
On the section. First in international news
This is that India and the UK have a comprehensive
Economic and Trade Agreement that is SETA
And the Agreement on Social Security has come
Into F. So India UK Comprehensive
Economic and Trade Agreement, which is
I have come. Recently, Andrew Burnham, who
He is the PM of the UK. He assumed
This is the office. Ok? new UK Prime Minister
Made by Andy Burnham. and PM Modi
Got an award again. Indonesia
Highest Silan Award of Bun Tang etc.
Puranas. This is the Adipurna of the Republic of
Indonesia. Who gave it? Prabowo Subian
has given it to him. Ok? Where?
in Jakarta, the capital of Indonesia
Is. Modi ji is watching award paid
I will take the award. Ok? The PM
announce announce that the Indian Institute
of management bore will establish its
Campus in Indonesia. and bore his campus
Will make it in Indonesia. PM also
Visited UNESCO World Heritage Site of
Praban Paraman Temple in Yogyakarta
Along with the Yoga Indonesian President
Prabhava subhiyanto। PM Modi has become the
First Indian PM to address the
Parliament of Indonesia. So first
became the Prime Minister who
Address to the Parliament of Indonesia
Have done. PM Modi who is India
He hosted the Australia Annual Summit.
Curry. You know, right now Australia and
Modi ji was on a visit to New Zealand. So
The third India Australia Annual Summit took place.
Hosted by the PM of Australia and
Melbourne. Ok? These were the outcomes.
What were the outcomes? Main Outcome Joint
The declaration came out from the defense and
Security Corporation Pay. India
Australia Maritime Security
Australia India Collaboration Road Map
Partnership on Cyber ​​Critical
Technology and Technologies and Supply
The CSIR & IP Australia in CHESS
Have entered into an agreement on access
To CSIR Digital Sort Traditional Knowledge
Digital Library OK Both Sides
Agreed to work towards an early balanced
Comprehensive Economic Cooperation
Agreement and the Long Term Pending
Administrative Arrangement under the Civil
The nuclear arrangement was operationalised.
Ok? So this thing has to be taken care of a little.
It's not that important, but still
You have to see it once. PM Modi again
Participate in what we were just watching
These are the additional details in it.
Ok? Let's move ahead. The Indian Council
of Agricultural Research ICR and
Agriculture Department Ministry of
Fisheries, Agriculture and Blue Economy
Both of them from the Republic of Seychelles
MOU signed. Just have to be careful.
What about the ICR and what about the Seychelles?
There is the Ministry of Fisheries. of Seychelles
What is the Highest Sell In Award? which gave
I went to Modi ji. So what is the order of the blue?
I had done it. Tell me quickly. Blue what's the name
was complete in which the Seychelles and the Republic of
The spelling itself was wrong. Türkiye has
The 2026 NATO summit is held in Ankara.
And Türkiye itself will host the 2026 event.
Cop number which is your conference of party
UF Triple C's No. 31. host this
Will do. Where will it be? This will take place in Türkiye.
Ok? The one from 30 was in Belém, Brazil.
Had happened. 32 Wali A Dees who is Baba
It will be there in Ethiopia. Ok? So
You have to keep this in mind. Ok? Seychelles Yes
Blue Horizon Blue Eyes. Nice Blue Harries
Are. Absolutely. India becomes a party too
The WTO Agreement on Fisheries
Subsidies by depositing its
Instrument of Acceptance. Ok? Bus
Take care. WTO Agreement of
Ah India Party Ban on Fisheries Subsidies
Has gone. Indonesia Sign a Contract.
This is important. Indonesia signed
Kiya Contract and Agreement to
Acquire BrahMos supersonic cruise missile
Indonesia will acquire it. And we are
Also in talk with UAE. India to UAE
Brahmos and our Akash Arrow missile
Our defense system is that of India and UAE.
We are talking together. Negotiations underway
Have been. Deal Involves Two Missile Batteries
Valued at roughly 630 million along side
Corporation for Astra MK1 Air to Air
Missiles. If we talk about Astra MK1
Astra, which is Mark One, is a bi-ram that
Is beyond visual range air to air missile.
The pilots here can't see.
are beyond visual range and air to air mark
She does. Ok? This is primarily by the
DRDO and manufactured by the Bharat
Dynamics Limited BDL. Ok?
The President of Ukraine who is approved
Serhiy Koretsky as the country's new prime minister
Minister. So he became the new Prime Minister of the UK.
Are. Don't think Zaleski is gone.
Zansky is the president there. He still
Yes, Zansky. Ok? Prime Minister of
That is what is being talked about here. Serhiy Koretsky
Are made. Ok? Senegalese President
Basiro Has Been Elected as the New
Chairman of ECOWAS that is Economic
Community of West African States. Who?
Basiro. Is it okay? Remember it by saying F. F
Kanishka Narayan is from Muzaffarpur, Bihar.
Are born. Ok? Kanishka Narayan. UK
that of artificial intelligence
This is the ministry that was created for the first time.
Is. So Kanishka became the first minister before him.
Narayan.
France Becomes First European Union
Country to Ban Social Media for Children
Below 15 years. Children below 15 years of age
France has completely
What has been banned? Social media. Correct
Is?
[deep breathing sound] [sudden sharp intake of breath]
And the MEA has withdrawn
[sound of clearing throat]
2017 notification that imposes certain
Conditions on Indian citizens travelling to
Yemen. So now the Ministry of
External Affairs banned the 2017
He was given a lift by Indians going to Yemen.
I have done it now. Ok? Next is N
Indian delegation visited Kyrgyzstan.
Can you quickly tell me the capital of Kyrgyzstan?
From. For the Inauguration of the International Center
For Civilization Studies Manas and Mahabharata.
Ok? International Center for Civilization
Studies Manas and Mahabharata. At their inauguration
Bishkek, the capital of Kyrgyzstan, is located here.
Have gone to. Ok?
[nasal sound]
Switzerland hold kare kare. will host
Where is the Global AI Summit? in Geneva
There will be a Global AI Summit. Ok? This meditation
Will keep it.
[deep breathing sound] [sudden sharp intake of breath]
which we hosted in the India Pavilion
Showcased his Orion. Galgotia's
Galgotia humiliated Galgotia as per the rules
It's done. Galgotia got it done. Both are there, right?
Both happened. Galgotia got himself embarrassed
And got it done for India as well. Guys
Thomson Assumes Charge as the New FATF
President. For 2026 to 28. India
Chard the Ninth Session of the Intergovernmental
Group of Experts on Consumer
Protection Law and Policy Organized by
The Uncut at Geneva, Switzerland. Ok?
You can see its details here
of Uncut. So India took over the chairmanship.
Of the ninth session. Ok? Joe Inter
There is a Governmental Group of Experts. Fund
Khare, who is the Secretary of the Department of
Consumer Affairs Representative India
and chaired the Ninth Session of the Inter
Governmental Group of Experts. On. Correct
Is? It is not that important. It is fine
A little bit. Ok. World Bank Board of
Executive Directors Approved 890
million dollar financing package for
India's National Rooftop Solar Program
PM Surya Ghar is a free electricity scheme under which
Under this, every household will get 300 units free every month.
for the purpose of providing electricity
Funding received from the World Bank is 890 million
of. Now let us come to the awards section.
Ok? Now we will see the awards.
Let's get started.
The first 72 National Film Awards
Let us see. Ok? which is the 72nd National
There are film awards. Best Feature Film
Got Article 3670. Best Actor in a
Leading role Mammoti for the Brahma Yugam. Correct
Is? It has a Malayalam feel and Kartik Aaryan
Best Actress in a Leading Role for Chandu Champion
Leading role: Yami Gautam for Article 370
Best Actor in a Leading or Supporting Role
Sanjay Mishra for Bhakshak Best Actress in a Leading Role
Supporting role Sachnamidas
For Maharaja and Rupashree Vargadi for
Mithya Best Debut Film of a Director
Randeep Hooda has got it. Ok?
The movie he made on Swatantra Veer Savarkar
Has made the best debut film of a
The director has received it. Ok? Veer Savarkar
So you do anything that means ruling
If you make the party happy, you will get an award.
will get. It is not that this is the current
It is the government. Any government may come tomorrow
Suppose Congress will come, then even before
It was Congress which made the government happy.
Will do. That's a different matter, yes, that means
There would have been some change from government to government.
Is. There are some governments which mean
very much supports that
If you make it in our favor. Ok? and this
It has been going on since before. Ok? Indira
It is from Gandhi's time, right? So you don't do this
Imagine that I am against some party.
I am saying no. I am neutral.
Ok? I am neutral. This balances me
Rajiv would have had to do it. Otherwise, to judge
There are a lot of people sitting for it. Ok? Best
Like I am one of you. Ok? For him
I am also a bit abusive. I gave him something like that
It won't hurt as much as it hurts him
It will happen that this will support my party.
Doesn't do. This is not from my tribe.
Isn't it? Best Non Feature Film Bhangar. Correct
Is? Bhangar and Best Documentary Ramnami
and Best Debut Film of a Director
Non-feature film, this was a feature film. These
Raviraj Murmu has got it. Ok?
Department of Jo Water Resources River
Development and Ganga regeneration is under the
Ministry of Jal Shakti
Has taken the Seventh National Water Awards. So
If we talk about the best state then it is fine
The award categories are Best State, Best
District, Best Urban Local Body,
Best Implemented
Project in the Water Sector and BEST
Industry. Ok?
So these are the categories under which the awards are given.
are given. 70 awards have been given. So
We don't need to remember that at all.
Which awards are there? Ok? So you
You can skip this. National National
[sound of clearing throat] Awards for E
Governance NAAC 2026 IT Recognize 17
Projects and Initiatives Across Seven
Award categories with 10 Gold Awards,
Six Silver Awards and One Zari
Award announced by the Government of
India. Ok? Where did it happen? So the national
The conference on e-governance is being held in Jaipur.
It was conducted in Rajasthan and
You can see the categories of Gold Winners here.
Can. No need to remember.
There are many. International Olympiad which
2026 was India did something quite remarkable in this
The performance is shown. Ok? So 56
International Physics Olympiad, 58th
There was chemistry. Then there was 37 Biology and 67
Was a Maths Olympiad. Ok? In this
How many and what gold medals have you won?
Who won is not important.
Ok? And by the way
It's not very important, really.
Should I tell you? Ok? that Physics Olympiad
How many medals did you get? Five gold medals out
Of five participant India Rank Joint.
First four gold medals out of four
Participant India Recorded Its Best
Performance Finish Joint First One Gold
and three silver every Indian
Participant won a medal. So, that much
It is not important. Just take a look.
Ok? This is important Lokmanya Tilak
National Award for someone who has done a lot for the country
He did well, he was given this award.
goes. So this is our NSA right now.
Yes Doval ji, he has met him. Musical drama
Academy Recognized Haveli Music by
Selecting Ahmedabad Scholar Acharya Shri
Ranchod
Ranchhod Lal Ji Goswami for the Ustad
Received Bismillah Khan Youth Award.
Whom? Ranchod the Ranchod Lal ji. Ok?
To Ranchhod Lal Ji Goswami.
This is very important. Very much.
Joe Poet, Poet and Lyricist from Tamil Nadu
Varamutu has been awarded the 60th Jnanpith.
The award has been given. Jnanpith Award India
is the highest literary award of the total
In how many languages ​​is it available? just
I will tell you. Ok? Second Highest Ah
What is the literary award? So you know that
It should be your Sangeet Natak Academy
There is an award. And how many languages ​​are there in total?
Are there? So there are total 23 languages.
Firstly, there are 22 languages ​​in the Eighth Schedule.
and apart from this the English language
In that too. Ok? Let's talk again if
Whose do you do? Then we can talk now
She is from the sports section. So first of all
The most important thing is the FIFA World Cup.
FIFA Men's World Cup in 2026. Three
Happened in countries. In the US, in Canada,
in Mexico. There were 16 cities that
Hosted. There were three countries. There were 16 cities. That
For the first time, three nations jointly hosted it.
Have done. Do you know? next time too
We
Next time too, only three nations will host it.
There are. Which were those 30 three nations?
Please tell me. Canada had debuted as an
The official World Cup is hosted by its host nation.
He had not done it before. Attention
Where will the one from 2030 be?
Portugal.
Morocco, an African country, and Spain
Who has won this year's FIFA World Cup.
So it will happen in these three countries. Team 48 was this
Last time it was 32. Each T in 12 groups
12 Groups of Four Teams Each. There were 12 groups.
Four teams in each group. 104 matches
Had played. Total was the mascot team this time.
From Canada was Maple the Moose. was from Mexico
Zayu was the Jaguar and USA clutch was the ball
It was Deagle. Ok? And we'll talk about the winner.
Spain. Spenceman has won the FIFA World Cup
Cup Once Before 2010. First win in 2010
Have already done. So he has won for the second time. So
Please take care. Ok?
And the runner up in this was Argentina. Ok?
Argentina won the 2022 one. previous
Argentina had won the match. And this time
Was runner up.
Cape Verde Second Smallest
Country after Iceland has participated till
Had done. Jordan Uzbekistan
He made his debut for the first time. Correct
Is? Brazil has won the most FIFA titles
I have won five times. 1958, 62, 70, 94,
He has not won any title since 2002.
So whatever this is like, our Indian is the most
Successful Hockey Team Throughout the Olympics
It is from India. Ok? But as much as these
This is our badge of success.
There were old players, they have given
Us. Ok? From 1928 to 1956
Won six consecutive gold medals. So this is his
Everything that we have today has been given to us somewhere or the other.
Sitting on top. in the same way as
What it used to be like for Brazil at that time
Pay
Ah, what was his name? Pele is very strong
Pele was the footballer of his time. Ok?
So he had Major Dhyanchand like us.
For example, in Indian hockey, Brazil has
For example, there was Pele in football. Germany and Italy
have won four and Argentina has won three, 1978,
In 86 and 2022. Talk about awards
The Golden Ball has been awarded to the player who
Of Spain. To whom is this given? Best
Who is a player. Not that the one who
who has scored the most goals
It is available. No, he gets the Golden Boot.
Whoever scores the most goals. Most
Number of goals. Ok? So most number of
Goals that are Kylian Mbappe are France
from they received they received this and golden
The glove that the goalkeeper gets is from the United
Simon has got it. Can someone tell me what the Greek
Simon is a footballer from which country? What
Is he the defender of the country? So he is from
Spain. Ok? who from Argentina
Also very strong perf means he is a defender.
Correct? He performed very well as a goalkeeper
Had done. If you've seen ah. Isn't it?
He had saved many and many
He used to give a lot of reactions, that best young man
Player who is Pau Cubasi
Ok
Come on, Neymar has announced that he
He retired completely
Le Li is a Brazilian international footballer.
I tried, I tried, now it's over, meaning
I tried, I tried, but I won.
Brazil never got its World Cup
He won the previous one in 2002 while living in
Well, since they've been playing
Brazil has not won any World Cup.
Junior Okay PV Sindhu here
History has been created by winning the Japan Open
She has become the first Indian to
Reigning World Champion Akane Yamagachi
hara hai and she became the first ever Indian
Player to Win a Title at the Japan Open
Congratulations to P Sindhu ji and
Again Historic Milestone Achievement by R
Women are doing everything in sports.
Hey boys, I don't know what they are doing.
are you blowing stuff
I mean Punjab is blowing the money
And you know how much drugs and so on
It's going on. Isn't it? and Punjab and Haryana
Jeans are meant to be very strong for athletes.
If we look at it sports wise, it is the same
It doesn't matter. as in Kals' Women
Bronze medal in discus throw also
found. I think I can't remember the name.
Is. I think both of them were from Haryana.
And one person came in third bronze and one in fourth
I came to Ok? So perform quite well
Our girls have been women
Okay, I just teach the girl [laughs].
That was right, we
You are right, come on brother, Indian women
Cricket Team Created History at Lord's
by beating England by 270 runs in the first
In the first ever women's test at the
Women's Venue. Ok? So at Lord's
It happened in England and England only
270 runs lost. Yastika Bhatia is the first woman
Bunty, who scored a Test century at Lord's
In the stadium. She is Yastika Bhatia and
Kranti God has taken five wickets.
Again Yastika Kranti name will be remembered.
Remember the Name The Commonwealth Games 2026 which will be held on 23
You have been inducted since July and August 2nd
till
Will go. That means we will continue till tomorrow and before
It was to be in Australia. Ok?
It was supposed to happen in Australia but could not.
[sound of deep breathing] in Australia
In Victoria. Glasgow, Scotland
He said no problem, we will get it done. Ok? So
Then it was done. Ok? And but all
There were no sports this time. Ok? Number
There were very few off sports this time.
16 sports. Ok?
Only 16 sports are being played this time
Meaning they were included. Ok? 16
Sports and the mascot is Pinni.
Glass vegan that is unicorn Finney. Ok?
Where will the next one be? The one of 2030.
Ahmedabad. It will be in Ahmedabad. Ok?
Ahmedabad.
Ok. Ok.
2026 Under 20 Asian Wrestling Championship.
It will be in Thailand. China ranked first
found. India got the second rank. India
Won 20 medals. In the wrestling championship.
Four Gold, seven Silver and nine Branch. Under
20th Asian Wrestling Championship.
Ok? I had a drink today.
This has been happening a lot since then.
Ok?
The name of the drink was quite obscene. So I tell
I can't. Ok? If someone drank
If it happens then he will know. Dash on the Beach.
Ok? I can't fill that dash.
Telangana will host the 8th Khelo India
Youth Games 2026 in November. Ok?
What will Telangana do to this? Host
will host the eighth Khelo India Youth Games
Him in November. Ok? Khelo India
University Games and Khelo India Winter
Games were introduced in 2020. play
India Para Games to be held from 2023
Started. You should know this thing.
Where did the Tribal Games take place recently? Why?
Tribal Games Fantastic.
Bro Code
Meaning tell me quickly Khelo India Tribal
Where were the games held recently and Khelo India
Where were the University Games held? So
The university ones were in Rajasthan.
And where did the tribal people take place?
It happened in Chhattisgarh. you should know
Needed We are located in Raipur, Jagdalpur, Chhattisgarh.
And it happened in three cities of Surguja. Correct
Is? So tribals happened in Chhattisgarh
Games are still the same as before and university games
Where did you go? in Rajasthan and
Which university topped?
Why? Which university topped this?
Did you do it? Which university topped? So
We are not the PDF of the class with space, sir.
Got it yet. Haven't you had it yet?
In that?
Why? Haven't you read it yet?
What does the app say?
[sound of clearing throat]
Come on, Vietnam will host the pickup ball
World Cup 2026 from 30th August to 6th
September Pickup Ball Combines Elements of
Tennis, Badminton and Table Tennis
It combines and Vietnam
Okay, and tell me what our 39
When will the National Games take place? In 2027
Will be. There will be no National Games in 2026.
Yes this time. So starting in 2027
And he will be in Meghalaya. So Vietnam
It will host. Take care Pickable World
Cup vs Rathnavel from Tamil Nadu becomes
India's 99th Chess Grand Master. 99 Chase
He has become a Grand Master. Ok? VS
Ratnavel. Ok? From Tamil Nadu. Indian
Grand Master Rohit Krishna wins gold.
Raja Ritwik Tech Silver at Menaris
International Chess Championship (which also took place in France)
is in. Ok? Rohit Krishna gets gold
And Raja Ritwik got silver.
Where will the 2026 E-Sports World Cup be held?
will be? In Paris France. World War II 2026
Who has won? Variant. By Janick Sinner.
By defeating who has defeated? Alexander
To Zebrev. And Linda won the women's singles.
Noskova from Church Republic. Whom
Has he defeated you? Why? Linda Noska
Who has defeated whom? New Delhi will host
has been 2
Commonwealth Table Tennis Championship. it
Don't relate it to the Commonwealth Games. Commonwealth
2017 Commonwealth Table Tennis Championships
This has nothing to do with games.
Have to be careful. Ok? And whom did they
Is it defeated? Lindasco even defended his own country.
Muchova has been defeated. Who defeated whom? Muchova
To. Of our own country, that is, of the Judge Republic
She was also there. Ok? Muchova.
Ok. Let's move on. Let's see next.
ICC Women T20 World Cup Australia
Has won. Won for the seventh time. Player of the
Series Bethany has been from Australia. And
Who have you defeated? To England. Ok? So
Beth Mooney
England will host Australia. England
Will Host Australia in the First Ever.
England will host Australia in the
First Ever Mixed Disability.
Ashes
ok Ashes cricket which will be test series
In 2027, the match between England and Australia
Whatever happens in India will happen in England, that means
That's right, ICC has banned Sourav Ganguly and Kevin
Pietersen and Anjum Chopra who were inducted into the ICC Hall of Fame
Of Fame, it is included in it. Ok?
These three people have now become 125 people.
He is in the ICC Hall of Fame. to leander paes
The player of the Asian Tennis Federation is
ambassador has been appointed who is the governing
Asian Tennis Association is the governing body for tennis in Asia.
Tennis Federation Leander Paes Anahat Singh
Again he has created history.
World Squash Junior Championships
Who did Canada defeat after winning it? Egypt
Rukaya Salim has been deported from Egypt for the last 16 times.
He was going to win this but Anahat Singh
He said, how do you wait like this, it's okay.
He is a 16 year old Egyptian boy who is wet
I broke it. wet means hey he
There is a drought of 16 years or for 16 years.
No medals were coming. won again
16 years of drought. So they were going to live
Now they have dried up. Meaning 16 year old soo wet
It's done for them. Ok? Dried up 16 years old
Wet. Squash is said to make its Olympic debut
Debut. So he is also going to make his Olympic debut.
Is. T20
Our 2020 is ours, cricket's year
That format will also be introduced. So it means
There is a chance that next time we will do much better.
I wish I could get a lot of gold medals. Ok? Well, further
Let's grow. Indian shooter Esha Singh Vaughan
Gold medal. So it is that brother is like an orphan
It is a lion. Okay, right? Seeing me this, he
It is understandable that brother, if children
If passion is followed from childhood
So can excel quite a lot. That's enough
Excel can do it. Ok? and as if
He excelled in many rooms.
But all these things are for rich people.
It looks a little more beautiful for me. our
Like for lower middle class poor people
It does not happen. This is the reality. Ok?
Let us get a job first. a little food and drink
Lets do it. We see this. Isn't it? We
Where should I practice questions?
Let us go.
So Indian shooter Isha Singh won the gold.
Manu Bhaker won the bronze medal. is in the
The 25 meter pistol event was held in
ISSF World Cup 2026 by Londo Norris
The Hungarian Grand Prix is ​​the one he won.
Taking the Checkered Flag Ahead of Max
Waston and Kimi Anton Leary are in now.
ok in appointment quickly
Let's see the appointment ok RBI has
Sir, you can still take classes.
What
Why do you just look at
Sir, yours is working.
The class is still going on. Will have to come.
You are great.
I want to study maths from you very comfortably. come
I will have to, brother. 11:00 am to 8:00 pm
Up to 9 hours continuously.
Remarkable. RBI has approved Ravi Shankar
As its new executive director. Correct
Is? Ravi Shankar has been appointed as the new
Executive Director. take care
RBI. The Government Gave a One Year
Extension to Foreign Secretary Vikram
Mistry sorry Mistry, say Mistry
You know the Foreign Secretary is there when
After this Pahalgam attack of yours,
We had counter attacks, okay?
Operation Sindoor was going on at that time
He used to do the same press briefings, then later
There were attacks on him as well as personal attacks.
You know he was Vikram Mishra.
f has been extended for one more year
Anurag Jain appointed as the new CEO of Nidhi
Chhabbar was made but he was removed
Now Anurag Jain has been made Pehle Toh Baby
V R Subramaniam was there. Then came Nidhi Chhabbar.
Then now Water Nidhi Chhabbar will not last long.
Didn't stop. And Anurag Jain has just been appointed as the new CEO
Was made. You will keep this thing in mind. And
Who is the Vice Chairman of NITI Aayog?
[nasal sound]
Why? Vice Chairman of NITI Aayog.
The Chairman is our Prime Minister.
So Ashok Kumar is the one who is Lahari. Correct
Is?
Let RBI approve NS
Vishwanathan's reappointment as not accessible
That's very important. Just look a little bit more
It is not important. Ok? Vishwanathan
Anand this isnt over as the toke over as the
Interim President of the Zofidia that is
International Chess Federation Interim
As President, he held office
Vishwanathan Anand ji has assumed this.
Prahlad Joshi becomes the new Education Minister
Are. So you must know this. Its
Which ministries did he hold earlier?
You can see it here. Ministry of
There have been consumer affairs. M
Ministry of New and Renewable Energy
Have lived. And now they have to pay additional charges.
Has been given. Ok? Ministry of
Education Ka After Dharmendra Pradhan
Resignation. And who has just been appointed secretary?
Are? Naresh Pal Gangwar ji has been appointed. Correct
Is? Higher Education Secretary. Ok? Naresh
Mr Pal Gangwar Ok. Ok? We
Ok? and T K Anil Kumar who is
Secretary, Department of School Education
Made for literacy. Vineet Joshi this
Earlier he was Secretary in Education, so he
Panchayat Raj was given that son, there is no one
Do a little here and there, people will think, oh
Look, the government has taken action now.
Ok? Keshav Chandra, Secretary, Ministry
of mines and this is already in the governments
Even if it were, it would not be like that. Ok? Ok.
We must keep the scales balanced. Chandra Bhushan
Kumar Chandrabhushan Kumar Secretary
Ministry of Labour and Employment in
Appointment made Sushil Kumar Lohani
Secretary, Department of Animal Husbandry
Husbandry and Daring Satyendra Singh
has been appointed Secretary of the Department of
of Urban Development and Dr. Srinivas Kumar
Tummala, whose secretary is he?
Belongs to the Ministry of Earth Sciences. Correct
Is? So this is most important, Naresh.
Pal Gangwar wali and T K Anil Kumar wali
and Vineet Joshi who was earlier in Education
In the ministry and now in Panchayati Raj
Have already done. Ok? Piyush Goyal has been
Appointed as the Secretary General of the
NHRC. So the National Human Rights Commission
Piyush has been made its Secretary General.
Goyal. NHRC you should know that it was formed in 1993
It was as a statutory body. Because this Act
It was made through. What does anyone say about you?
Are?
[sound of deep breathing]
What do you say? Meaning, any constitution
There is no article in . like national
There is a commission for SC, Article 338, ST,
338A is backward classes 338B. But
It has no effect. It was made in 1993
As a statutory body, retirees are sorry
[nasal sound]
[sound of deep breathing]
Admiral Joe is retired, Admiral C
Raghuram was appointed CMD
Of Hindustan Shipyard Limited. incomparable
Mishra assumed charge as the Chairman and
Managing Director of Hindustan Copper
He assumed the role of HCL Limited.
Anupam Mishra took charge. Ok? Become MD
It belongs to Hindustan Copper Limited. Harjeet
Singh Grewal has become the chairman of the National
For the Commission for Minorities.
Ok? The National Commission for Minorities is
a statutory body of the government of
India that safeguards and protects the
Interest of Minority Communities. it was
set up under the National Commission for
Minorities Act of 1992 and its head
Quarters are in New Delhi. Ok? New
Its headquarter is in Delhi. Ok? And
You can read some of the appointments here.
Just by myself.
Ok.
Let's come to the defense now.
Let's come to the defense.
All right. So the Indian Navy has commissioned
I have done its sixth project. Ok?
Wait a second.
So the Indian Navy commissioned the sixth
Project Joe 17
Is it A or the 17 alpha indigenous?
Telescope Frigate Mahendragiri F38 AT
Details of Visakhapatnam Project 17A are
Nilgiri class frigates developed here
It is being done because the first one was yours
NS Nilgiri had Project 17 Alpha and
Project 17 is precisely the Alpha Seven chips.
There are total four bays to be developed
Mezgong Dop Ltd. Okay.
One second.
Let's IS and three will be developed here
by Garden Reach Shipbuilders and
Engineers Limited. Ok? Four MDLs
And will develop three GRSCs. Ok? And
If we talk about ships then IAS
Nilgiri, Himgiri, Udaygiri, Dunagiri,
Taragiri, Vindhyagiri, Mahendragiri these
All your mirrors will be developed. MDL
Delivered Udayagiri in July 2025 end
Mahendragiri Inn
April 2026. So keep this thing in mind
Is. Ok? Is it clear? Ok. and Dunagiri
If we talk about this then this is also news
I was. Developed by GRSC.
This was done in Kolkata. Isn't it?
was included. And
This was the fifth Nilgiri class.
stealth guided missile frigate
What did Modi ji do? This one
was inducted into the Indian Navy in this manner
IAS Dunagiri IAS on 21 June 2026
Researcher and IAS forward, do you know IS?
Last month we read this news IAS
Dunagiri IAS Researcher
And yours
IAS Agra is fine, induct these three
Shyama Prasad Mukherjee Port was established
More Gardens in Kolkata, West Bengal
Reach Ship Builders & Engineers Ltd
Developed by DRDO conducted a
Successful flight test at Pinaka Long
Range Guided Rocket at the Integrated Test
Range at the Chandipur. Ok? So the Rocket
Was tested for a user-defined minimum
Range of 60 km Unlikely Older Unguided
Pinaka Rockets LRGR is a guided
Weapon. So It Can Strike Targets More
Accurately over much larger ranges. So DRDO
Has successfully conducted flight test range.
Whose? Pinaka Long Range Gain Rocket
ITR at Chandipur. Indian Navy Commissioned
Malvan was commissioned. The Second of the Mahe
Class Anti-Submarine Warfare Shallow
Watercraft. Anti-Submarine Warfare Shallow
Where is the watercraft IAS Malwan built?
to be done? in Cochin Shipyard Limited and
The two classes are Arnala class and
Mahe Class You Can Watch Arnala Class
Build by GRS. and Mahe class
If we talk about Cochin Shipyard
Ltd. and this is your IAS Malwan
Belongs to the Mahé class antisubmarine
Warfare Shallow Watercraft. The Indian Navy
Hosted the Operation Southern Readiness 262
OK at the Southern Naval Command in Kochi
Okay, so this is something you need to keep in mind.
Southern Redness 262 He holds this someone.
Tray This is not a classic war game
It is training centric, this is fine and also
Many countries participated in it
Nearly 40 nations have said where Southern
Indian Air Force at Naval Command Kochi
has commissioned its participation in the
Royal Australian Air Force Premier
Multinational Air Combat Exercise Joe Pitt
It is black. Pitch Black Exercise Joe is where
Where was it conducted? Darwin
July 20 to August 7 in Australia
In between. And where else? Australia.
It's a simple thing. And Indian in this
The Air Force has participated. This too
It is a multinational exercise. That means a lot of
Countries participate in it.
Defence Minister Rajnath Singh flagged in a
Circumambulation of the sea. The First Ever Try
Services All Women Circumnavigation Sailing
Expedition.
Ok? So flagged is the sea
To pradakshina. Now the Indian Army Sailing
Vessel. Ok? Triveni Nine Women Officer
of the three services return to Mumbai after
Successfully completing the 314-day journey
After completing it, this is your Triveni.
Triveni Vasal is one of the nine women officers in
Yes, she has returned. Ok? So this is your attention
Have to keep it. Ok? circumambulation of the sea
DRDO conducts maiden flight test
of Kusha Long Range Surface to Air Missile
from APJ Abdul Kalam Island of the
Coast of Osa. Ok? This long range from you
He will directly ask what is Kusha? So it
Is long range surface to air missile. So
Made in flight, that is, the first flight traced
And this was your success. The US has
Editions hosted
[sound of clearing throat] is the rim of
Pacific that is remade in 2026 in Hawaii. Correct
Is? It is the world's largest international
It is a maritime exercise. Ok? Worlds
This is the largest. And that has been the theme of 26
She has been Partners Integrated and
Prepared. Ok? India has developed its
First Indigenous Expendable Turbojet
Engine in the 350 kg thrust class. Who?
Have you developed it? DRDO's gas turbine
There is a research establishment, he said. Ok?
Expendable turbojet engine. Indian Army
Is raising specialized falcon battalion. Whom
To manage? which are UAVs,
There are drones to manage them.
To Baaz Battalion, that is, especially to them
In UAEs, in UAVs, that is, in drones
The train will be done. Commonwealth War Graves
Commission Recognized 9909 Previously
Uncommissioned British Indian Army servicemen
From World War One. Ok? So again
He has got recognition in a way.
CSIR's National Aerospace
Laboratories have in bore completed the design
Face of Sarus Mark Two. Who? CSIR's
The National Aerospace Laboratory. Now
Let's see some science and tech news.
Are. So the sky route, the aerospace
Sky Route Aerospace Pvt. Ltd.
Is. This is our space agency. of India
It is the first private space agency. He mission
Under arrival [sound of clearing throat]
Successfully Vikram Van from Sriharikota
Has been launched. Ok? Modi ji again
Both the founders of Sky Route also met
It is from them.
The Milestone Mission Places Six Payloads
into a 450 km In low Earth orbit.
Ok? Ok? Vikram One is India's
First Privately Developed Orbital Class
Launch Vehicle Built by Sky Route
Aerospace. You should know this.
DRDO has launched indigenous
i.e. indigenous underwater fiber optic
Sensing system. Underwater fiber optic
The sensing system has been developed here by DRDO.
A complete trap has been laid. to establish a sea
Bed Surveillance Network in the Indian Ocean.
So in the Indian Ocean properly
So that surveillance can be done. Therefore, DRDO
It has been developed here. ISRO
conducted the first ground test of the
Solid Motor for the Sub-Orbital Launch
Vehicle for Experiment Solve at the Satish
Dhawan Space Centre in Sriharikota. Ok?
So ISRO conducted the first ground
Test of the solid motor. Ok?
ISRO conducted a critical integrated main
Parachute Air Drop Test I Mat 05 for the
Gaganyaan Missions at the Aerial Delivery Research
and Development Establishment Drop Zone
In Shivpur, Madhya Pradesh. So Shivpur Madhya
It has been conducted in the state. Correct
Is? Aerial Delivery Research Development
Gun missions for the establishment that you
I know it will most probably go in 2028. Correct
Is? And sent three astronauts under him
Will go into space through us. So his
So when he comes back he will be there for the same
Drop test which is successfully shopper
Conducted in Madhya Pradesh. Space
SpaceX owned by Elon Musk
Launched Bor the World's First Commercially
Build Nuclear Power Satellite
Nuclear power satellite. commercially
Build Nuclear Power Satellite Around the World
to abort a Falcon or rocket during the
Transporter 17 Mission. So Falcon Nine
It is launched from a rocket which is your
It is a reusable vehicle.
Indian Origin NASA Astronaut Anil Menon
This is Soyuz's MS 29 spacecraft.
International Space Station
I do you know when how many eight months
are going on a research mission to
International Space Station: What you need to know
Should when was it developed in 1998 okay
The world of 2026 is artificial
Intelligence Conference in Shanghai The Formal
Signing by 29 countries to establish the
World Artificial Intelligence Cooperation
An organization will be formed. 29 countries have
I have signed it. Math which is your ministry
of Information Technology in collaboration with
Drone Federation of India Latch Second Edition
of the National Innovation Challenge. that much
It is not important. Ok?
You can do the dodge ones yourself. Correct
Is? Important days and their themes here
It is written. Now come Books and Authors
Pay. So the first book is our Chief
Our Justice was Justice Gavai.
[deep breathing sound] [sudden sharp intake of breath]
So Vice President CP Radhakrishnan from 49
The book of the Chief Justice has been released.
The Voice of Justice Justice Gwai Speaks.
Ok? Only one book is important. The rest come
They are on government schemes. Ok? Our
I think this last section will be government
Schemes. Ok? We
[nasal sound]
There is such a community in Manipur also.
Let us go
Hum Chalo To The Union Cabinet Has Approved
The Mobile Phone Manufacturing Scheme with a
Budgetary outlay of this much ₹62,500 crore. So much
Mobile Phones with Budget Outlay
Manufacturing Scheme which is Union
The cabinet has given its approval. of the scheme
The tenure will be 5 years. From 2026 to 27
It will happen by 203031. Ok? What is M?
Indian brands to achieve technological
Sovanity. He should achieve it. Ok? Union
Cabinet has approved the Semicon 2.0 for
The Development of India Semiconductor Design
and manufacturing ecosystem with a total
Budget outlay of this much. Ok? SEMICON 2.0
has been approved. develop semiconductors
To do this, the semiconductor industry
To develop.
The Union Cabinet has approved India
Industrial development plan chemicals and grand.
Chemicals Scheme for Establishing Three
Dedicated chemical parks in the country.
Ok? Three dedicated chemical parks developed
will be done under that. Under whom? gorgeous
Under the Chemicals Scheme. Ok? The Scheme Was
Announced in the budget for 2026-27
Was done. Budget outlet worth around Rs 330 crore
Is. And the scheme is for 5 years
It will work. From 2627 to 3031. digital
India Program Completed 11 Years on 1
July 2026. Ok? Launched on 15 May 2015
Was. Ministry flows. Ok? This is something
And you can see the initiatives. advanced
Bharat Ji Ram Ji from 1 July 2026 this
It has been enforced. It has been implemented. Correct
Is? When Bibi Ji Ram Ji Act came, yours
Well then? Developed India Guarantee for Employment
and livelihood mission under it by July 1, 2026
Your lunch has already started.
In which 100 means 25 days guaranteed
You will get employment. unskilled labor
Unskilled employment. Ok? First
Ma'am, under NREGA, there were 100
It was day employment. you should know
You should know that this was launched in 2005.
It was NREGA and in 2009 it became MG NREGA
And now he has brought Lord Ram in his place.
Has gone. Ok? Look at the rest of this
Will take. This is part of static. From here
This also becomes a question. National SC ST
The Hub scheme was launched in 2016.
Had gone. He has completed 10 years. and this
This is a scheme of the Ministry of MSME. Correct
Is?
Atal Vayo Abhudaya Yojana. Ok? about this
You should also know a little bit about
Which is its ministry? Social Justice
and empowerment. Well, who is its minister?
Are? Why? Who is its minister? Social
Of Justice and Empowerment. So our Ramdas
Athawale ji is the one who, in some strange way
Let's say. You must have heard Abhijeet.
Abhijeet Deepak's is also in a strange way right now.
At least something was addressed. He came from America
by doing something like this
His name is secretly from America.
Abhijeet Deepak Well then Central Sector Scheme
is this for senior citizens ok and it
was earlier known as National Action Plan for
Senior Citizens and Was Revised and Renamed
This was done in 2021. 5 years have passed
This. PM Modi launches The Next Face of
Udan and inaugurated the new terminal
Building at the Jodhpur Airport. Ok?
So fly away from the city. that I told you first
It was only told that it was launched in 2016 and
Its
I innovated the new fuzz. The Cabinet
Approved on 25th March 26 for the financial year
2026 to 27 to Fiscal Year 35 to 36 with a
Total outlay of Rs 2840 crore. Ok? coming now
It is on government bills. One is FCRA.
The bill was in the news a lot. Ok? Foreign
Contribution Regulation Act which does
Used to be? Amending the old Act.
The Act came into force in 1976. Whose
For? The Original Legislation Enacted Tonitor
and regulate the acceptance and
Utilization of foreign contribution of
Individual Association Companies. So any
Foreign Individual Association or Company
In India, if any NGO etc.
If he is giving donation then to regulate it
This Act was brought for this. in 2010
It replaced the 1976 legislation.
Was. Ok? Some amendments have been made and now
Key amendments that have been proposed.
Like for example, the first punishment in this
There was a provision for it to be 5 years old.
It has been reduced to one year. And
A lot of changes have been made here.
Successive Legislative Changes Introduced
Title Compliance Norms Mandatory Basis
Requirements for Office Bearers
Restrictions on Administrative
Expenses and the Prohibition of
Transferring foreign funds to other entities.
So a lot of changes have been made since 2000
Or Act 26 has just come. Ok? and one more
So that is the biggest change. Ok? Who
There is an amendment bill of 2026 that Amit
Shah says. Ok? that if this
Is it implemented, right? So whatever this
Rights etc. are being done in Manipur etc.
All these will be closed because they need foreign
Funding is available. Ok? So foreign funding
This will stop it. And I will take care
what has been done in this and not valuation if any
Whatever penalty will be imposed, that will be the impairment.
The penalty will be reduced from 5 years
It has been extended to one year. it has been reduced
The time period of impression. your gift
Prevention of Unfair Public Examinations
Means Amendment Bill of 2026. Correct
Is? it seeks to amend the public
Examination Prevention of Unfair Means
Act of 2024. Ok? The Act Aims To
Prevent Unfair Means in Public
Examinations conducted by specified
Public Examination Authorities. These include
What? UPSC, SSC, Railways
Recruitment Board which is RRB your railway
He conducts the exam. Institute of
Banking Personnel Selection, NTA,
Ministries of the Central Government and
Their attached offices, other authorities
Notified by the Central Government. So,
The examinations conducted by them
Let's go. Ok? This is for all those exams.
Your public examinations will be applicable
Prevention of Unfair Means Act of 2024.
Now what is there in this Act? What was it? 2024
I came, you know that. And now this
What is proposed in the amendment bill?
Has been done? So, this protest of yours
If it has happened then after the protest many
Changes are proposed here. As
that if use of unfair means is made
Impression by any person
There will be impression. Earlier it was 3 and 5 years
And fine up to 10 lakhs
[sound of clearing throat]. what are you doing now
given? Imprisonment between 5 and 10
Years. You will get 5 to 10 years of impression and
Fine up to Rs 50 lakh. Unfair Means By
A service provider fine up to ₹1 crore. 1
Fine up to crores. Or if it's here
If you do this bill, you will face a fine of up to Rs 5 crore.
Up to 1 crore here and 5 crore here
Up to. Ok? It has just been extended.
Persons in charge of service provider if
If we talk then those who are in charge of the service
Provider's impression between three
And 10 years and a fine of ₹1 crore. Now!
Minimum imprisonment of 5 years and fine of ₹5
A tax of crores has been imposed. But not the same
If you get caught, you will not get a clean chit.
Then how will it work? It is organized crime
If the impression was earlier than 5 to 10 years
Between and find not less than a crore.
What's up now? Minimal impairment was done
7 years of imprisonment and the minimum fine imposed
He will definitely be fined up to Rs 10 crore.
Will go. Ok? PM Modi announced a high
Power Task Force Led by Nandan Nilkani to
Bring the
Reforms in the Examination System.
Ok
Is it clear? So this has to be kept in mind. and this
How many members are there in it? It is not written
Is. There are six members. Nandan Nilekani has been
Interested by the Center for Several
Initiatives. So you can see it here
Which initiatives do they care about?
Has been done before. The one that is UIDI
They have already taken the lead. cofounder of Infosys
These are they. Ok? So this has to be kept in mind.
Their entire committee has six members.
There are residents. Ok? Six members of these
There are residents. Which members are these?
So, one has been the former chief of ISRO.
Our S Somnath of IIT Madras who
Priyanka Gandhi had made fun of it
A little talk about cow urine in Parliament
K.V. Kamakoti Tapan Deka who is in the IB
Director is from former and education
Former Education Secretary Anil Anita
Karwal and Amrita Lal Meena Okay I will write
I am giving you one here, our Somnath ji
Yes S Somnath
ok and tapan deka
Former Director of IB Kamakoti V
Kamakoti
Anita Karwal, Director of IIT Madras
Ok
Anita Karwal and Amrit Lal Mee
Okay Amrit Lal, I'm okay, let's come now.
The last section is Pay and that is Reports and
Rankings. So the Economist Intelligence which
The unit is EIU. It has global liveability
Index has been released for 2026 which
Evaluates 173
Cities World Wide Across 30 Indicators.
Ok? So the city which is at number one in this
That's your Copenhagen. and Indian
If we talk about the ranking of cities, then New
Delhi at 120th position, Mumbai at 121st position
Chennai is at 123rd position and Bor is at 127th position.
The number is here. Ok? then either
Even Indian cities did not make it to the top 100.
I have found it. Top Ah First Number Pe Rahi Hai
Copenhagen, Denmark. Ok? Economist
The Intelligence Unit releases this
To the Global Liveability Index. Indian i
Performance and Status India Achieved Its
Higher Highest Ever Position Ranking 94 Out
of 169 countries with an overall score of
68.3 was out of 100. Okay? So this is for you
Have to be careful. India's performance
It has been quite good at this. Highest Ever
Position ranking 94 out of 169 countries.
The score was 68.33.
NITI Aayog has released the report titled
Strategic Road Map for Making Ayeda
Global. So just keep this in mind. Road Map
proposes 500 crores
Bioeconomic Growth Fund for the Year 2026 to 35
For the period of . How much fund is this proposal?
He does it, he suggests it, keep that in mind
Is. Ok? What was the title? Strategic
Road Map for Making Ayeda Global. Ok?
This one report was released. A study
Report on low participation in Gram Sabha
Across States and UTs. that the village council
There is less participation of people in it.
Road Map for Building India as a Leading
Bioeconomic Power House by 2035.
NITI Aayog released a report on
Investment Friendliness Index. Correct
Is? In the Investment Friendliness Index
A report was released by NITI Aayog
Is. Announced in the Union Budget of 2026.
If we talk about the performance category in this
If you do, you will be a top performer, a front runner,
Emerging Performer and Aspiring State Key
Here are the categories. in which
If we talk about overall performer, top overall
Performers are from Gujarat, Maharashtra,
Tamil Nadu, Goa and Osa. Last
Gujarat ranks first in the state rankings.
Used to be. Then Maharashtra and Tamil Nadu. So
You have to keep this in mind. Joe's Last City
Gujarat was at the first position in your category.
Is. Then Maharashtra and then Tamil Nadu. Ok?
and in hilly and north eastern states
Uttarakhand is on the first position.
Union Minister of Education releases the
Report on Performance Grading Index
2.0 for States and UTs and Performance
Grading Index for Districts for
2526. 1000 in PGI States and UTs
Points across 70 indicators are listed here
Have gone. It's not that important
Framework. Ok? I will take care of you.
Ministry of Education performance
Redding Index Release 2.0
Union Minister of Ministry of Education
Release a Report on Unified District
Information System for Education Plus UDA Plus
Your Udice Plus 2025 26 on School Education
In India. If we talk about gross in this
Enrollment ratio in the middle category and
89.6 in the secondary category in 2025-26
has been in the middle category and secondary
71.7 in the category
The Union Ministry of Education released the
Reports of the All India Survey on a Higher
Education Ash for the year 2022 to 23 and 232
Gross Enrolment Ratio Gross Enrolment
Ratio is computed as a ratio of
Student Enrolled Enrollment to Total
Population in the age group of 18 to 23
Years. How many children are enrolled and
What is the population between 18 and 23 years?
According to the 2011 census. So it is 29.5
Is. Ok? In 202-23 and in 2023 it
It has increased to 30. Female Joe Gross
The enrollment ratio has increased from 31.2, sorry.
31 has increased from 30.2 to 31.2.
Tamil Nadu is ranked first for
Higher Education Gross Enrolment Ratio
Tamil Nadu recording 52.3% in 2023-24
It has been at number one. Ok? Let us go.
[sound of deep breathing] Okay. OK the ratio
Gross Enrolment Ratio to Male to Female
Is computed as the Gender Parity Index
which measures the relative access to education
of males and females and JPI for
2023-24 was 1.08 this report wali jo
Our video will come tomorrow. Tomorrow
It will be telecast on this channel at 10:00 am. So
You will see it is completely covered there.
Details there. GPI stands for
That it gives the ratio of female to male. So
If the ratio of females to males is 1.08 then
Gross enrollment of women
The ratio is higher as compared to male.
Ok? It's obvious. The Ministry of
Cole Released RO. India's First Report
On Scientific Mind Closure and Repurposing
Practices. So the Ministry of Coal
Release it RO. India Global Passport
Ranks at number 125 in the index.
Sweden is at number one. Ok?
Who has been the publisher? Global Citizen
Solutions.
Ok? in the Global Passport Index
According to Time Out's 2026 survey, the
Jaipur ranks sixth among the worlds
Happiest Cities Earning the Distinction of
Being the only Indian city in the top 10. Correct
Is? It is not that important. just a little bit
Take care. The Unite Act report that came
Under that, FDI in India is more than 44%.
has increased to US dollars. 39 billion has passed
Is. 39 billion in 2025.
UN Releases Its First Scientific
Assessment of Artificial Intelligence in
July 2026 Under the Title Preliminary
Report of the Independence International
The Scientific Panel on AI is the first scientific
UN released the report of assessment AI
Okay and let's see the bitchurries. So Bichuriz
I know that the New Zealand actor Sam
Neil, he has died. Girish Bhardwaj
The Bridge Man of India has died.
Who received Padmashree in 2017.
Garfield Sobers West Indies Legend In
Cricket Great Crickets Greatest
All-rounder Dies at 89, He Became the First
Cricketer to Hit to Hit Six Sixes in
a single over in first-class cricket in
You should know that the cricketer of the
The award is given by ICC.
The trophy Sir Gair is named after him.
Field Sobers Trophy is very important
Yes, this is right, this is Sobers' non-field
take care okay because of these
The trophy for best cricketer is given in the name
If yes, then it is correct that he was from West Indies.
Former Afghanistan cricketer Shapoor
He has died suddenly. very young age
He has died in 2017. Someone I think
somewhere in the pancreas or liver
He had a problem. At a very young age, their
Death has occurred. Let's go
[sound of clearing throat]
So playback singer S Janaki passed away ah
In Mysore, Karnataka. Sahitya Akademi Award
Winning Tamil Writer Pomani. Ok?
Celebrated for his realistic
Portrayals Passed Away and Tamil Poet Too
Time Sahitya Akademi Award
Puvirasu also died. To all
The important Garfield is sobbing. This meditation
Please keep it. Ok? Ok
Is it clear?
All right. Thank you everyone. Thank you.
How long will you get the bomb shot done? The exam date is
Let it come.
Let the exam date come brother. then
Will get it done. Tell me how to get it done now.
Yes.
CGL 26 is expected in October.
Let's get the PDF of this.
Parmar Academy's free content section and
Rest of this on Parmar SSC's telegram channel
There are batches, the rest you should know now
Another batch has been added and that is
Repeaters batch of Prashant Sir is still there
What do you watch live?
Is it still live?
Brother, I have to agree
have to admit
Keep doing it until it is deleted
Go sir
I have to admit brother, this sir is new.
Yes, you know brother, your Prashant brother
I would like to request each and everyone of
I am asking you to take the test for your batch.
I have already done pre videos, is it okay?
If it is helpful then you will know about it.
will go will go. Ok?
Otherwise this is Uday Sir's foundation batch.
Uday Sir also has a revision batch. means maths
But now it is all around, meaning there will be no shortage.
It is not the one. Ok? You will also need to do reasoning
I know there are all batches. Ok? Thank you
Everyone. Thank you. A How much funding has been received?
Funding will have to be checked. let me see for a second
What? How much funding has been received so far?
There will be a link here. Here is the link.
It shows in the link here. this funding
How much has happened?
Funds are used for Assam relief only and now
Till now the collection here is Rs 44,000 and
413 people have donated. Great and we
How much will he donate from his side?
I will tell you. Ok? Later, first class ends
Let it be. Thank you everyone. Thank you.
Thank you.
Ok? And this monthly magazine also comes.
You should know about current affairs. They
You will see it in the course section of Current Affairs
Will go. Ok? Monthly Current Affairs
Banking OK Thank You